what's up guys coach Brett Contreras
here today I'm going to go over the
Viking press
which I really want to stress for
straight coaches or anyone who's prone
to experiencing shoulder or low back
pain with standard military presses so
I'm a huge fan of the military press but
if I do too often
it hurts my clavicles it you know here
to take my shoulders but also most
people just because you can't be in
neutral and do a military press because
your hands in way so you have to lay
back a little bit but with the military
but it's most people you know as they
wrap to the failure or approach of women
back then I'm leaning more and more so
some people end up get getting you know
lumbar hyperextension related back pain
so if you're in this category or if you
just want to try something new
here's what I want you to try the Viking
press now it cost some money so
obviously and it there's an extensive
setup required but if you're a gym
enthusiast like me maybe I'll inspire
you to make a couple purchases this is
the Viking press attachment now I got
this from elite MTS it's also available
from Black Widow training gear so this
is the Viking press which I'll discuss
in a minute and then this here is a rod
and pivot available through black widow
training gear this thing's cool as hell
I don't use this because I've got an
adjustable leg mine unit which I believe
I got from été but I'm not sure because
I got a did like a second
but I think Petey was the manufacturer
anyway what you need to do this the
Viking press is a popular lift it's
strong man
so we're replicating that strongmen
exercise but I found that just with the
biomechanics you don't want this down at
the crown you don't want this in a
normal vampire
you know ground ground apparatus because
you'll start out and it's so angled you
are not pushing outwards you want this
to replicate overhead pressing and so
you want the consistent torque angle
curve on the shoulders so if you notice
I have this a little bit higher than
shoulder level it's like mid mid middle
of my my head right and you'll see what
that looks like once I perform the
exercise but let's say you don't have
one of these you can buy the rod and
pivot what this does is this you'll use
in the power app and you can put this so
this the barbell fits through here so
you'll have it out like this but this
guy you can get these in different
diameters to match the safety pin that
your power rack has so imagine this
going through a safety pin and just
swiveling like that and then you can
clip use a clip on one end and use a
squat stand on the other end and you can
go like that now I don't have it is this
because they because I have this and B
I've got the suspension straps which I
like more than the safety pins but again
this is available through blackboard of
training here and then I'm going to take
now I'm going to take the Viking press
once I perform this I have the option of
using narrow neutral grip wide neutral
grip for pronated grip
I've only stuck to narrow neutral grip
so I thought this safety squat sorry
take this deal I have a squat stand here
and I position this real close to the
end here because if I have this I hear
there's give me a lot of flex in the
it's gonna bend if you lot of wear and
tear on your barbell so I put it right
close to the edge and then all I'm gonna
do I take the neutral grip with the
narrow get close lift it out perform
some reps come down wallah
so once again this is the Viking press
key features make it hitch from up high
and mid head level as he come up push
through and make sure you full extension
I like the narrow neutral grip and what
you'll find is you're not gonna hyper
its skin with these Yvonne you are going
super heavy and even when wrapping to
failure so please give it a try and let
me know what you think